Guide to the J. Hector St. John de Crèvecoeur Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
J. Hector St. John de Crèvecoeur papers
1784-1880
1784-1810
GEN MSS 722
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.55
(6 boxes)
The J. Hector St. John de Crèvecoeur Papers consist of manuscripts and printed material documenting aspects of the later life and work of the French author, best known for his 1782 Letters from an American Farmer.
St. John de Crèvecoeur, J. Hector, 1735-1813
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Almost all of the papers were purchased from the 19th Century Shop on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund and the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2006.
The 1784-1786 letterbook of Crèvecoeur family correspondence was purchased from the William Reese Company on the Henry C. Taylor Fund, 2006.
The corrected proofs of Voyage dans la Haute Pennsylvanie et dans l'Ètat de New-York were purchased from the William Reese Company on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2006.
Custodial History
Christie's New York sale, 2001 October 29.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
J. Hector St. John de Crèvecoeur (1735-1813)
J. Hector St. John de Crèvecoeur was born and educated in Caen, Normandy. In 1755 he became a surveyor in the French Colonial Militia and fought at the battle of Fort George in 1757. Crèvecoeur was wounded at the battle of Quebec, after which he left the army for unknown reasons and sailed to New York in December, 1759. On arrival, he changed his name to J. Hector St. John. For the next decade, Crèvecoeur earned his livelihood as a trader, explorer and surveyor, traveling through all of the British North American colonies. He became a naturalized citizen of New York Colony in 1765.
In 1769 he married Mehitable Tippet, the daughter of a prominent Dutchess County family, and purchased 120 acres of farmland in Orange County. The next several years brought Crèvecoeur three children and increasing prosperity; his farm flourished,and he led a county project to drain arable meadows and reclaim farmland. Crèvecoeur kept a daily journal of observations on his experiences and on his adopted country, which he considered "the most perfect society in the world."
The advent of the American Revolution disrupted this happiness. Crèvecoeur's attempts to remain neutral won him suspicion and hostility from both sides of the conflict. In 1779, he decided to return to France to establish his children's right to inherit the family's lands in Normandy. Arrested by the British in New York City as a suspected enemy collaborator, he was imprisoned for months, but finally sailed for Europe in September of 1780. His ship was wrecked off the coast of Ireland, and he did not reach Normandy until August of 1781.
Crèvecoeur's Letters from an American Farmer was published in London early in 1782. It received international praise, appeared in several English and Irish editions, and was translated into German and Dutch. On the verge of America's independence, Crèvecoeur was the first author to provide an answer to the European question of the day: "What then is this American, this new man?"
Crèvecoeur was considered one of the foremost European authorities on the new country, and France appointed him consul to New York, New Jersey, and Connecticut. He sailed for New York on the ship that carried the first copy of the Treaty of Paris to the United States. When he arrived, he discovered that his wife had died and his children had been taken in by their neighbors; his farm and its buildings had been destroyed by Native American allies of the British.
As Consul, Crèvecoeur worked to increase French-American trade and supported cultural and artistic exchanges. He was also a patron of botanical gardens, experiments with steamships, and the first Roman Catholic church in New York City. His greatly enlarged and reorganized French version of Letters was published in Paris in 1784. His many American friends included Thomas Jefferson and Benjamin Franklin. St. Johnsbury, Vermont, was named after Crèvecoeur, in 1789 he was made a member of the American Philsophical Society.
Crèvecoeur returned to France in 1790, but the dangers of the French Revolution led him to retire unpensioned in 1792 and to withdraw into his family life. In 1801 he published his Voyage dans la haute Pennsylvanie et dans l'Ètat de New York; the work was not popular, and was not translated into English until 1961. Crèvecoeur spent his final years at his farm in Lesches, France, and visiting his extended family. He died at Sarcelles, near Paris, in 1813.
Scope and Contents
The J. Hector St. John de Crèvecoeur Papers document aspects of the later life and writings of J. Hector St. John de Crèvecoeur, particularly the expanded French version of his Letters from an American Farmer (1784) and his final work, Voyage dans la haute Pennsylvanie et dans l'Ètat de New York (1801). The collection includes family correspondence, manuscripts, and research materials, mostly focused on social and political conditions in the United States during the first decades of its existence as a nation.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Correspondence and Family Papers, 1784-1880. II. Writings, 1786-1801. III. Research Materials, 1784-1812.
Travelers' writings, French; New York -- Description and travel; Pennsylvania -- Description and travel; United States -- Description and travel; United States -- Description and travel -- Early works to 1800; United States -- Social conditions -- To 1865; United States -- Social life and customs -- 1775-1783; United States -- Social life and customs -- 1783-1865; St. John de Crèvecoeur, J. Hector, 1735-1813; St. John de Crèvecoeur, J. Hector, 1735-1813 ( Letters from an American farmer); St. John de Crèvecoeur, J. Hector, 1735-1813 ( Letters from an American farmer, French); St. John de Crèvecoeur, J. Hector, 1735-1813 ( Voyage dans la haute Pensylvanie et dans l'état de New-York)
- Correspondence and Family Papers, 1784-1880, undated; Series I; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged by type of material and then alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I includes correspondence and family papers. Correspondence includes a letterbook containing letters from Crèvecoeur and from members of the French nobility to his sons. Family Papers include biographical notes compiled by Crèvecoeur's grandson and accounts from Crèvecoeur's attempt to run a packet-ship service.
  - Letterbook, 1784-1786 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    23 letters from Crèvecoeur to his sons, Guillaume-Alexandre and Phillippe-Louis, almost all in English, containing discussion of the boys' educations and social development; Crèvecoeur's business affairs, including his attempt to establish a packet-ship service between France and the United States; and his progress on the third volume of Lettres d'un cultivateur Amèricain.
    With 3 letters from Crèvecoeur's daughter, America-Frances ("Fanny") to her father and 30 letters from various members of the French nobility addressed to Crèvecoeur's sons. Correspondents include the comtesse d'Houdetôt, Crèvecoeur's patron; the duc de la Rochefoucauld-Liancourt, and the Baron de Breteuil.
  - Accounts, 1794-1795 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Accounts related to the packet-ship service started by Crèvecoeur.
  - Biographical notes and correspondence calendar, 1880, undated (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
    Notes compiled by Robert de Crèvecoeur during his research for his biography of his grandfather ( St. John de Crèvecoeur: sa vie et ses oeuvres, 1883). Includes chronologies, a calendar of correspondence, notes on various persons, and brief essay drafts.
- Writings, 1786-1801, undated; Series II; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  Series II contains manuscript and annotated printed material related to two of Crèvecoeur's works, Lettres d'un cultivateur Amèricain and Voyage dans la Haute Pensylvanie et dans l'Ètat de New-York.
  - Lettres d'un cultivateur Amèricain, undated
    - Les Treise Chapitres du Troisième Volume du Cultivateur Amèricain, 1786 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Autograph manuscript, heavily corrected and revised, of twelve of the seventeen chapters of the third volume of the French version of Letters from an American Farmer.
      Bound in: printed pamphlet, Extrait des gazettes amèricains (Paris, 1786).
  - Voyage dans la Haute Pensylvanie et dans l'Ètat de New-York
    - Manuscript
      - Autograph draft fragment, circa 1794-1800 (Box 2, Folder 7-9)
        Includes Précis du Chapitres au Second Volume (18 p.); À George Washington (20 p.); notes on William Penn; and notes numbered 22-60, presumably for a chapter in the work.
      - Map: Jonction des Rivières Delaware et Susquehannah, undated
      - Map: The Southern Parts of the Patent of Elisian Fields, undated
      - Wrapper, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Printed
      - Volume I, 1801 (Box 2, Folder 11)
        Heavily corrected and annotated in Crèvecoeur's hand, with new manuscript pages tipped in.
      - Volume II, 1801 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Volume III, 1801 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Research Materials, 1784-1812, undated; Series III; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  Series III contains manuscripts by Crèvecoeur, other manuscript materials, newspaper clippings and newspapers, and printed material, almost all documenting Crèvecoeur's research on aspects of the United States. Manuscripts in his hand include extracts from other works on the United States; a discussion of Franco-American relations; and a notebook containing statistics on various American states. Other manuscript material includes a copy of a John Fothergill letter and a description of George Washington's entrance into New York.
  Newspaper clippings, sorted by topic, were collected by Crèvecoeur and reflect his interest in such subjects as religion in America, American educational institutions and learned societies, and slavery.
  - Manuscripts in Crèvecoeur's hand
    - Notebook, circa 1805 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Contents include extracts from Michaux's Travels to the Westward of the Allegany Mountains; notes on the new state of Ohio; descriptions of Native Americans ("Sauvages"); descriptions of Annapolis, Mount Vernon and Monticello; and brief entries on a variety of other topics.
      Also includes an eight page summary of The Three Sultanas, accompanied by a printed title page, and several pages of pasted-in newspaper clippings on American subjects.
    - Notebook: Sundry and Gleanings, 1810-1811 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      Notebook compiled during a trip to Munich. Contents include statistics concerning the United States, including populations of the states and territories, distances between major cities, and amounts of agricultural produce. Also contains notes on European history and law. Title from front cover.
      Also contains: Postschrift von Deutschland...1793.
    - Notes on French-American Relations, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Manuscript, incomplete, discussing the situations and conditions of Francophone residents of the United States and Canada; the promotion of emigration from France to America; and Franco-American trade relations.
    - Notes on a mechanical device, circa 1800? (Box 4)
      Notes, mathematical calculations and a drawing of a mechanical device.
      Written on the reverse of Map of the Middle States of North America with Part of Canada, shewing the situation of the principal towns, viz. Columbia, Baltimore, Philadelphia, New York, Newport (Rhode Island) Boston & Montreal, also their several communications with respect to Lake Ontario. undated.
    - Unidentified notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Other Manuscripts
    - Arrivée du General Washington, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Convention Generale à Philadelphie, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
      List of the contents of three notebooks (not present) documenting the Constitutional Convention.
    - Letter from John Fothergill to a Gentleman of Massachusetts-Bay, undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
      Copy of a letter originally dated October 20, 1780 in which Fothergill discusses the War of Independence and the possible future relationship of Great Britain and the former colonies.
    - Letterbook, 1796-1797 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      Copies, in English and French, of brief letters concerning trade between the United States and France.
    - Order de la grande procession que eu lieu let 4 juillet 1788 à Philadelphie, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Plans and elevations of buildings and gardens, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Politique. Encyclopedie, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - Fiscal and monetary concerns, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Literature and philosophy, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Native Americans, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Natural history and other scientific topics, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Navigation and travel, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Official statements, decrees, and parliamentary reports, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Religion in America ( Religions en Amerique ), undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Slavery, undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Universities, schools and learned societies ( Universites et etablisments publiques en amerique ), undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Miscellaneous topics ( Melanges ), undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Newspapers
    - The Independent Chronicle and the Universal Advertiser, 1784 January 1 (Box 5)
      Contents include an announcement by Crèvecoeur ("St. John") of the publication of the Journal de medicine.
    - Le Moniteur Universelle, 1812 May 7 (Box 5)
      Contents include a lengthy Extrait d'une lettre du president de l'Universitie de New-York.
  - Printed Material
    - A Plan of Captain Carver's Travels in the Interior Parts of North America in 1766 and 1767, 1778? (Box 5)
    - Memoire aux consuls de la Republique Française, 1802 April 28 (Box 5, Folder 36)
      Annotations in Crèvecoeur's hand on blank final page.
      Date given in original as: 10 floréal an. 8.
- Oversize, 1.67; (1 box)
  - Map: Jonction des Rivières Delaware et Susquehannah, undated (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 37)
  - Map: The Southern Parts of the Patent of Elisian Fields, undated (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 38)
  - Carte generale des Ètats-Unis, de l'Amerique septentrionale, undated (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 39)
  - Postschrift von Deutschland...1793 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 40)
  - Notes on a mechanical device, undated (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 41)
  - Plan of a garden, undated (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 42)
  - The Independent Chronicle and the Universal Advertiser, 1784 January 1 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 43)
  - Le Moniteur Universelle, 1812 May 7 (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 44)
  - A Plan of Captain Carver's Travels in the Interior Parts of North America in 1766 and 1767, 1778? (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 45)